# Minal Suresh Patil

Contact Mit-huset Voice: (+46) 0738192248 Information Dept. of Computer Science Fax: 090-786 61 26

> Umeå Universitet E-mail: minalsp@cs.umu.se

Umeå, 901 87 Sweden WWW: https://minalspatil.github.io

RESEARCH INTERESTS My research interests lie at the intersection between formal methods, verification and software engineering, particularly in applying formal methods to ensure provable reliability guarantees to AI-enabled software systems.

Keywords

Safe and Trustworthy AI, Formal Methods, Verification, Cyber-Physical Systems

EDUCATION

### Umeå Universitet, Umeå, Sweden

Oct. 2020 - present

Ph.D. Candidate

Wallenberg AI, Autonomous Systems and Software Program

- Topic: Safe and Trustworthy Machine Learning: Robustness, Explainability, and Verification in Adversarial and Autonomous Systems
- Advisor: Kary Främling

## University College London, London, United Kingdom

Sept. 2018 - Sept. 2019

MSc., Data Science and Visualisation

- Dissertation Can we understand how demographics, product usage, revenue and product movements affect customers up-sell and cross-sell journey in the telecommunications sector?
- Advisor: Kira Kempinska

### R.V. College of Engineering, Bengaluru, India

Sept. 2011 - Sept. 2015

B.E., Computer Science

• Dissertation Topic - Fuzzy Graph Clustering for Image Segmentation

**Publications** 

M.S. Patil, Gustav Ung, Mattias Nyberg. Towards Specification-Driven LLM-Based Generation of Embedded Automotive Software. In Submission to Artificial Intelligence International Symposium On Leveraging Applications of Formal Methods, Verification and Validation (AISoLA), 2024

M.S. Patil and Kary Främling. Enhancing Vulnerable Class Robustness in Adversarial Machine Learning. In Proceedings of IEEE World Congress on Computational Intelligence (IEEE-WCCI): International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN), 2024

M.S. Patil and Kary Främling. Investigating Lipschitz Constants in Neural Ensemble Models to **Improve Adversarial Robustness.** In Proceedings of 7<sup>th</sup> International Conference on System Reliability and Safety (IEEE-ICSRS), 2023. 🔀

M.S. Patil and Kary Främling. Improving Neural Network Verification Efficiency through Perturbation Refinement. In Proceedings of 32<sup>nd</sup> International Conference on Artificial Neural Networks (ICANN), 2023. 🔀

M.S. Patil and Kary Främling. Do Intermediate Feature Coalitions Aid in the Explainability of Black-Box Models?. In Proceedings of 1st World Conference on eXplainable Artificial Intelligence, 2023

M.S. Patil. Towards Preserving Semantics Structure in Argumentative Multi-Agent via Abstract Interpretation. In Proceedings of 3<sup>rd</sup> Online Handbook of Argumentation for AI (OHAAI), 2022

M.S. Patil. Modelling Control Arguments via Cooperation Logic in Unforeseen Scenarios. In Proceedings of Thinking Fast and Slow and Other Cognitive Theories in AI of Fall Symposium Series at 36<sup>th</sup> Association for the Advancement of Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), 2022

M.S. Patil. Explainability in Autonomous Pedagogically Structured Scenarios. In Proceedings of Workshop on Explainable Agency in Artificial Intelligence at 36<sup>th</sup> Association for the Advancement of Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), 2022

M.S. Patil. Towards Explainable Agency in Multi-Agents Systems Using Inductive Learning and Answer Set Programming. In 6<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Automation, Control and Robotics Engineering (IEEE-CACRE), 2021 (oral presentation)

PATENTS

• Patil, M.S. 2019. *Method and System for Geo-Psychographic Segmentation Using Location Data and Learning models.* Indian Patent 201841034549, filed September 11, 2018.

## Professional Experience

#### Scania CV AB, Södertälje, Sweden

PhD Research Intern

Feb. 2024 - Apr. 2024

- Lead the development of a framework for generating secure C code, known as spec2code, designed to meet both formal and informal specifications using Large Language Models.
- Submitted a paper on this work to the conference.

### Virgin Media, London, United Kingdom

Research Intern

Oct. 2018 - Sept. 2019

- Developed a halo-forecasting model for customer up-selling opportunities, leveraging a blend of location data, transaction histories, and customer profiles, resulting in an accuracy of 83.4%.
- Implemented advanced ensemble methods, including Random Forest and Gradient Boosting, to improve the predictive performance of the model.
- Analysed and processed a large-scale dataset of 70,852 customers and over one million transactions, extracting actionable insights for targeted up-selling strategies, resulting in a 15% increase in customer conversion rates.

## Propinquity Labs, Bengaluru, India

Geospatial Data Scientist

June 2016 - Sept. 2018

- Led and managed a high-performing team of deep learning geospatial scientists and engineers to develop cutting-edge solutions for geospatial data analysis and interpretation.
- Spearheaded the implementation of a spectral land-use change detection model for environmental monitoring in satellite imagery, improving precision by 20% and reducing false positive rates by 30%.
- Conducted a comprehensive evaluation of different deep learning architectures and performance metrics for geospatial image analysis, optimizing model selection based on accuracy, precision, and computational efficiency.

Sensus Labs, San Francisco, California, United States

- Developed filter-based navigation algorithms (Kalman Filters and other linear and non-linear filters) to fuse information from a variety of sensors (IMU, GPS, magnetometer, static/differential pressure, cameras, etc.) reducing position error by 30% compared to traditional sensor fusion techniques.
- Conducted a comparative analysis of different Kalman filter variants for warehouse logistics tracking system in GPS-denied environments, optimising performance metrics such as mean squared error (MSE) and root mean squared error (RMSE).
- Collaborated with a team of engineers to develop a real-time navigation guidance system for autonomous systems, achieving sub-centimeter accuracy in various navigation scenarios.

#### Services

EXTRAAMAS 2023 (Reviewer), ICANN 2023 (PC-member), ICANN 2024 (PC-member)

### COMPUTER SKILLS

- Languages: C++, Python, OCaml, Rust, SQL
- Verification Tools: Lean and Coq (proof assistants), TLA+ model checker, Frama-C, Dafny
- Frameworks: PyTorch, TensorFlow, Vertex AI, GCP
- Tools and Technologies: Docker, Kubernetes, Git
- Operating Systems: Unix/Linux